By now you've seen the anomaly
ここまでで我々は
detection algorithm and we've
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを見てきた。
also talked about how to
また、アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを
evaluate an anomaly detection
どう評価するのかも見てきた。
algorithm. It turns out,
実は、実際に
that when you're applying anomaly
アノマリー検出を適用してみると、
detection, one of the
それがどれだけ
things that has a huge
うまく機能するかに
effect on how well it
巨大な影響を与えているのは
does, is what features you
なんのフィーチャーを使うのか、
use, and what features you choose,
何のフィーチャーを選んで
to give the anomaly detection algorithm.
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムに与えるか、という部分だ。
So in this video, what I'd
だからこのビデオでは、
like to do is say a few
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムに
words, give some suggestions and
食わせるフィーチャーを
guidelines for how to
どうデザインするか、どう選ぶかについて
go about designing or selecting
二、三の助言、
features give to an anomaly detection algorithm.
提案をしたいと思う。
In our anomaly detection algorithm,
我らのアノマリー検出のアルゴリズムにおいては
one of the things we did was
こんな種類のガウス分布を用いて
model the features using this sort of Gaussian distribution.
フィーチャー達をモデリングするという過程があります。
With xi to mu
xiを、ミューiと
i, sigma squared i, lets say.
シグマ二乗iで。
And so one thing that
そうであるから、私が良く
I often do would be to plot the
やる事としては、
data or the histogram of
私のアノマリー検出のアルゴリズムに
the data, to make sure that
データを食わせる前に
the data looks vaguely
このデータのヒストグラムをプロットしてみて
Gaussian before feeding it
なんとなくガウス分布っぽいかを
to my anomaly detection algorithm.
見てみる、という事があります。
And, it'll usually work okay,
あなたのデータがガウス分布でなくても
even if your data isn't Gaussian,
普通はオーケーです。
but this is sort of a nice sanitary check to run.
だけどこれは、実行してみるに値する、良いサニティチェックです。
And by the way, in case your data
ところで、あなたのデータが非ガウス分布をとっていても、
looks non-Gaussian, the algorithms will often work just find.
アルゴリズムは普通に正しく機能する事が多い。
But, concretely if I
具体的に見ると
plot the data like this,
データをこんな風にプロットしてみて、
and if it looks like a histogram like
ヒストグラムがこんな感じに見えたら
this, and the way
ところでヒストグラムの
to plot a histogram is to
プロットの仕方は
use the HIST, or the
hist関数を
HIST command in Octave,
Octaveでは使いますが
but it looks like this, this looks
そこでこんな見た目なら、
vaguely Gaussian, so if
これはだいたいガウス分布っぽい。
my features look like this,
つまりフィーチャーがこんな感じなら
I would be pretty happy feeding into my algorithm.
アルゴリズムに、とても幸せな気持ちで食わせられる。
But if i were to plot a histogram of my
だが、もしもデータのヒストグラムをプロットしてみたら
data, and it were
それがもしもこんな感じなら、
to look like this well, this
うーん、
doesn't look at all like a
こいつはベル型のカーブには
bell shaped curve, this is a very asymmetric distribution,
まったく見えないなぁ。 これはとても非対称な分布だ。
it has a peak way off to one side.
これはピークが片側に偏り過ぎている。
If this is what my data
もしこんな風に私のデータが見えたら
looks like, what I'll often
私が良くやる手段は
do is play with different
様々なデータ変換を試して
transformations of the data in order
もっとガウス分布っぽく
to make it look more Gaussian.
見えるようにする。
And again the algorithm will usually work okay, even if you don't.
繰り返しになるが、別にそんな事しなくても、だいたいはアルゴリズムはちゃんと機能する。
But if you use these transformations
でももしこれらの変換でデータをより
to make your data more gaussian, it might work a bit better.
ガウス分布っぽく見えるように出来たら、そっちの方がアルゴリズムはちょっとだけ改善される。
So given the data set
だからこんな見た目の
that looks like this, what I
データセットが与えられた時、
might do is take a
私が試すだろう事は
log transformation of the
logをとってデータを変換し
data and if i
その後に
do that and re-plot the
データをヒストグラムとして再プロットして
histogram, what I end up
この例の場合は例えば
with in this particular example,
結果としてこんな
is a histogram that looks like this.
ヒストグラムを得る。
And this looks much more Gaussian, right?
こっちの方がガウス分布っぽいでしょう？
This looks much more like the classic
こっちの方がより古典的な
bell shaped curve, that we
ベル型のカーブに見える。
can fit with some mean and variance paramater sigma.
それはある平均と分散のパラメータでフィッティング出来る。
So what I mean by taking
ログ変換を取る、と言っているのは
a log transform, is really that
具体的には
if I have some feature x1 and
あるフィーチャーx1があったとして、
then the histogram of x1 looks
そのx1のヒストグラムがこんな見た目だとすると
like this then I might
フィーチャーx1を
take my feature x1
log x1で
and replace it with log
置き換える。
of x1 and this is
そしてこれを
my new x1 that I'll plot
新しいx1とみなし、
to the histogram over on the right, and this looks much
それのヒストグラムを右にプロットすると、
more Guassian.
よりガウス分布っぽくなっている。
Rather than just a log transform some other things you can
log変換の他に、選択肢として考えられる物は
do, might be, let's say
異なるフィーチャー
I have a different feature x2,
x2があったとして、
maybe I'll replace that will
それをlog(x+1)で
log x plus 1,
置き換える、
or more generally with log
またはより一般に
x with x2 and
log xのxをx2とある定数c で
some constant c and this
置き換えた物で置き換える、というのが考えられる。
constant could be something
この定数cはいろいろ調整して
that I play with, to try to make it look as Gaussian as possible.
なるべくガウス分布っぽく見えるようにする。
Or for a different feature x3, maybe
他には別のフィーチャーx3に対し
I'll replace it with x3,
x3をルートを取った物で
I might take the square root.
置き換えても良いかもしれない。
The square root is just x3 to the power of one half, right?
ルートってのはx3の、単なる1/2乗に過ぎない、でしょ？
And this one half
そしてこの1/2というのも
is another example of a parameter I can play with.
いろいろ調整する事が出来るパラメータとなる。
So, I might have x4 and
x4があったとして、
maybe I might instead replace
そのx4を代わりに
that with x4 to the power
x4の違う指数乗、例えば
of something else, maybe to the
1/3乗とかで
power of 1/3.
置き換えても良い。
And these, all of
そしてこれら全て、
these, this one, this
これ、この指数乗の
exponent parameter, or the
パラメータ、または
C parameter, all of these
パラメータCも、
are examples of parameters that
これら全てがあなたのデータを
you can play with in order
ちょっとでもガウス分布っぽく見せる為に
to make your data look a little bit more Gaussian.
いじれるパラメータの例となる。
So, let me show you a live demo
ではここで、私のデータを
of how I actually go about
実際にいろいろいじって
playing with my data to make it look more Gaussian.
よりガウス分布っぽくする生のデモをお見せしよう。
So, I have already loaded
その為、ここに既に
in to octave here a set
Octaveにロードしておいた、
of features x I have a thousand examples
幾つかのフィーチャーxを。千のサンプルをここでは
loaded over there.
ロードしておいた。
So let's pull up the histogram of my data.
では私のデータのヒストグラムを出しておこう、
Use the hist x command.
このhist xのコマンドで。
So there's my histogram.
これが私のヒストグラムだ。
By default, I think this
デフォルトだと確か
uses 10 bins of histograms,
この10個のビンをヒストグラムは使うと思うが
but I want to see a more fine grid histogram.
私はもっと粒度の細かいグリッドのヒストグラムを見たい。
So we do hist to the x, 50,
だからhistに x, 50と渡す
so, this plots it in 50 different bins.
これは50個のことなるビンでプロットする。
Okay, that looks better.
オーケー。良くなった。
Now, this doesn't look very Gaussian, does it?
現在のところ、これはそんなにガウス分布っぽくは無い。でしょ？
So, lets start playing around with the data.
だからちょっとデータをいじってみよう。
Lets try a hist of
まずhistの
x to the 0.5.
xの0.5乗を試してみよう。
So we take the
つまりデータのルートを取って
square root of the data, and plot that histogram.
そのヒストグラムをプロットする。
And, okay, it looks
オーケー。ちょっとガウスっぽく
a little bit more Gaussian, but not
なってきた。だがまだまだだね。
quite there, so let's play at the 0.5 parameter.
ではこの0.5というパラメータをいじってみよう。
Let's see.
どうなるか？
Set this to 0.2.
これを0.2にセットする。
Looks a little bit more Gaussian.
もうちょっとガウス分布っぽくなった。
Let's reduce a little bit more 0.1.
もうちょっと減らして0.1にしてみよう。
Yeah, that looks pretty good.
いえーい！凄い良くなった！
I could actually just use 0.1.
これは実際だったら0.1で良い気がするね。
Well, let's reduce it to 0.05.
さらに減らして0.05にしてみよう。
And, you know?
ご想像の通り、、、
Okay, this looks pretty Gaussian,
よし、これはいい感じにガウス分布だ。
so I can define a new
だから新しいフィーチャーとして
feature which is x mu equals
xミュー イコール xの0.05乗
x to the 0.05,
と定義する。
and now my new
するとこの新しいフィーチャー
feature x Mu looks more
xミューは、以前のよりも
Gaussian than my previous one
よりガウス分布っぽくなって、
and then I might instead use
これを代わりに
this new feature to feed
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムに
into my anomaly detection algorithm.
食わせても良い。
And of course, there is more than one way to do this.
もちろん、これを行う方法は一つだけでは無い。
You could also have hist of log of
histのlog xというのも試しても良い。
x, that's another example of a transformation you can use.
それはもう一つの試してみる価値のある変換の例だ。
And, you know, that also look pretty Gaussian.
そしてこれも、見ての通りなかなかガウスっぽい。
So, I can also define x
だからxミューを
mu equals log of x.
log xと定義しても良い。
and that would be another
これもまたなかなか良い
pretty good choice of a feature to use.
フィーチャーのチョイスといえる。
So to summarize, if you
まとめると、データのヒストグラムを
plot a histogram with the data,
プロットしてみて、
and find that it looks pretty
それがだいぶガウス分布っぽくなかったら
non-Gaussian, it's worth playing
今回試したような変換で
around a little bit with
ちょっとデータをつついてみるのは
different transformations like these, to
試してみる価値がある。
see if you can make
もうちょっとガウス分布っぽく
your data look a little bit more
ならないかなぁ、と
Gaussian, before you feed it to
学習アルゴリズムに食わしてみる前に。
your learning algorithm, although even if
やらなかったとしても、
you don't, it might work okay.
たぶんうまく機能するけどね。
But I usually do take this step.
でも普段、私はこのステップを踏む。
Now, the second thing I want
ここで二番目に話したい事として、
to talk about is, how do
アノマリー検出に使うフィーチャーを
you come up with features for an anomaly detection algorithm.
どう見つけるか、というのがある。
And the way I often do
私が良くやるのは
so, is via an error analysis procedure.
誤差分析の手順だ。
So what I mean by that,
それの意味する所は
is that this is really similar
教師有り学習での
to the error analysis procedure that
誤差分析の手順と
we have for supervised learning, where
本当に似た物で、
we would train a
そこでは完全にアルゴリズムを
complete algorithm, and run the
学習させて、
algorithm on a cross validation set,
それをクロスバリデーションセットにかける、
and look at the examples it gets
そして間違いのサンプルを見る、
wrong, and see if
そしてフィーチャーを追加して
we can come up with extra features
それがクロスバリデーションセットで
to help the algorithm do
誤りだった物を
better on the examples
正しく扱う助けとなるかを
that it got wrong in the cross-validation set.
見てみる。
So lets try
ではこのプロセスを
to reason through an example of this process.
例を通して見てみよう。
In anomaly detection, we are
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムにおいては
hoping that p of x will
通常のサンプルについてはpのxが大きく、
be large for the normal examples
アノマリーなサンプルでは小さくなる事を
and it will be small for the anomalous examples.
期待している。
And so a pretty common problem
だから、良くある問題としては
would be if p of x is comparable,
pのxが同じような値という場合、
maybe both are large for both the normal and the anomalous examples.
例えば普通の物とアノマリーな物が両方とも大きい場合などだ。
Lets look at a specific example of that.
その具体例を見てみよう。
Let's say that this is my unlabeled data.
これが私のラベル無しデータとする。
So, here I have just one
ここではたった一つのフィーチャーx1しか無いので
feature, x1 and so I'm gonna fit a Gaussian to this.
これをガウス分布でフィッティングする。
And maybe my Gaussian that I fit to my data looks like that.
そしてフィッティングしたガウス曲線がこんな感じだったとしよう。
And now let's say I have an anomalous example,
そしてアノマラスなサンプルがあったとしよう。
and let's say that my anomalous example
そしてそのアノマラスなサンプルはxの値
takes on an x value of 2.5.
2.5を取るとする。
So I plot my anomalous example there.
このアノマラスなサンプルをプロットしてみた。
And you know, it's kind of buried
すると見ての通り、
in the middle of a bunch
それはたくさんの普通のサンプルの中に
of normal examples, and so,
埋もれてしまっている。
just this anomalous example
つまりこのアノマラスなサンプルは
that I've drawn in green, it gets a
緑で描いた物だが、それは
pretty high probability, where it's the
とても高い確率となる。それは青い曲線の
height of the blue curve,
高さで表される訳だ。
and the algorithm fails to
そしてアルゴリズムはこれを
flag this as an anomalous example.
アノマラスなサンプルだとフラグづけする事に失敗してしまう。
Now, if this were maybe aircraft
ここで、これは航空機エンジンの
engine manufacturing or something, what
製造とかだとしよう。
I would do is, I would actually
ここで実際に取れる対策としては
look at my training examples and
トレーニングサンプルを実際に見て、
look at what went wrong with
うまく行っていない特定の不良エンジンについて
that particular aircraft engine, and
どこが悪くなっているかを調べる。
see, if looking at that
そしてもしそのエンジンを調べていて
example can inspire me to
それにインスパイアされて
come up with a new feature
新たなフィーチャーx2を思いついたとする。
x2, that helps to distinguish
それがこの不良エンジンを
between this bad example, compared
識別するには有用な訳だ。
to the rest of my
残りの赤いサンプル、
red examples, compared to all
私の全ての正常な航空機エンジンと
of my normal aircraft engines.
比較して。
And if I managed to do
そしてなんとかそこまで行ったら
so, the hope would be then,
以下のような事を期待する訳だ:
that, if I can create a
新しいフィーチャーx2を作って、
new feature, X2, so that
私のデータを再プロットしたら
when I re-plot my data, if
トレーニングセットの正常なサンプルは
I take all my normal examples
プロットしてみたら
of my training set, hopefully
正常なサンプルは
I find that all my training
赤いバツのサンプルは
examples are these red crosses here.
こんな感じで見えたとして、
And hopefully, if I find
アノマラスなサンプルは
that for my anomalous example, the
フィーチャーx2が
feature x2 takes on the the unusual value.
異常な値を取るという風に出来る事を期待する訳だ。
So for my green example
例えば私のこの緑のサンプル
here, this anomaly, right, my
このアノマリーは
X1 value, is still 2.5.
x1の値は2.5のままだけど、
Then maybe my X2 value, hopefully
x2の値は例えば、
it takes on a very large
とても大きな値とか、
value like 3.5 over there,
こっちの3.5とかそういう値か、
or a very small value.
またらとても小さな値を期待する訳だ。
But now, if I model
ここでこのデータをモデリングすると、
my data, I'll find that
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムは
my anomaly detection algorithm gives
まんなかのあたりの領域のデータに
high probability to data
高い確率を与え、
in the central regions, slightly lower
そのちょっと低い確率がこの辺に、
probability to that, sightly lower probability to that.
それよりさらにちょっと低い確率がこの辺に、となる。
An example that's all the
そしてこの遥か遠くのサンプルに対しては
way out there, my algorithm will
私のアルゴリズムは
now give very low probability
ここではとても低い
to.
確率を与えるだろう。
And so, the process of this
つまりこのプロセスは
is, really look at the
実際に間違いだった物、
mistakes that it is making.
アルゴリズムがフラグ付けに失敗した
Look at the anomaly that the algorithm
アノマリーを直接調べて、
is failing to flag, and see
それが新しいフィーチャーを作るよう
if that inspires you to create some new feature.
インスパイアしてくれるかどうかを見てみる。
So find something unusual about
その航空機エンジンの
that aircraft engine and use
何か普通で無い所を探して
that to create a new feature,
それを用いて新しいフィーチャーを作る。
so that with this new
この新しいフィーチャーで
feature it becomes easier to
正常なサンプルとアノマリー達を
distinguish the anomalies from your good examples.
より簡単に区別出来るようになるように。
And so that's the
以上が誤差解析の
process of error analysis
手順であり、
and using that to create
それをアノマリー検出に使う
new features for anomaly detection.
新しいフィーチャーを作るのに使うやり方だ。
Finally, let me share with
最後に、私が普段
you my thinking on how I
アノマリー検出のフィーチャーを選ぶのに
usually go about choosing features for anomaly detection.
どうやってるのかについて、私の考えを共有しておきたい。
So, usually, the way I think about choosing features is
普段私がフィーチャーの選択についてどう考えているかといえば、
I want to choose features that will
アノマリーのサンプルだと思う時には
take on either very, very
なるべく凄く凄く小さくなるか
large values, or very, very
凄く凄く大きくなるような
small values, for examples
フィーチャーを
that I think might turn out to be anomalies.
探したい、と考えている。
So let's use our example
ここでも再びコンピューターのデータセンターの
again of monitoring the computers in a data center.
モニタリングの例を考えてみよう。
And so you have lots of
たくさんのマシンがあって
machines, maybe thousands, or tens
たとえば何千とか何万とかのマシンが
of thousands of machines in a data center.
データセンターにあるかもしれない。
And we want to know if one
そしてマシンの一つが
of the machines, one of our
コンピュータの一つが
computers is acting up, so doing something strange.
いかれているか、つまり何か妙な事をしているかを知りたい。
So here are examples of features you may choose,
そこでこんなフィーチャーを選ぶかもしれない。
maybe memory used, number of disc accesses, CPU load, network traffic.
メモリー使用量とかディスクアクセスの回数とかCPUロードとかネットワークトラフィックとか。
But now, lets say that I
だがここで、失敗してるケースの一つに、
suspect one of the failure
私のデータセットの失敗してるケースの一つが、
cases, let's say that
CPUロードとネットワークトラフィックが
in my data set I think
共にリニアに増えていくと
that CPU load the network traffic
疑っていると
tend to grow linearly with each other.
しよう。
Maybe I'm running a bunch of
例えばたくさんのwebサーバを走らせていて
web servers, and so, here
そのサービスの一つが
if one of my servers is
たくさんのユーザに対して
serving a lot of users,
サービスを提供していたら
I have a very high CPU load, and have a very high network traffic.
とても高いCPUロードと高いネットワークトラフィックを得るだろう。
But let's say, I think,
だが例えば、
let's say I have a suspicion, that
失敗のケースの一つは
one of the failure cases is
もしコンピュータの一つが
if one of my computers
無限ループで固まってるジョブを持っていると
has a job that gets stuck in some infinite loop.
疑ってるとしよう。
So if I think one of
つまり私は
the failure cases, is one of
ある失敗のケースは
my machines, one of my
あるマシンの
web servers--server code--
あるweb server、もといサーバーのcodeが
gets stuck in some infinite loop,
無限ループで詰まってる、と思ってるとすると、
and so the CPU load grows,
その時はCPUロードは上がるだろうが
but the network traffic doesn't because
ネットワークトラフィックは上昇しないだろう。
it's just spinning it's
何故ならそれは単に糸車がくるくると回っていて
wheels and doing a lot of CPU work, you know,
たくさんのCPUの仕事をしている、つまり
stuck in some infinite loop.
無限ループに詰まってる。
In that case, to detect
その場合、その種のアノマリーを
that type of anomaly, I might
検出する為には、
create a new feature, X5,
新たなフィーチャーX5として、
which might be CPU load
CPUロードをネットワークトラフィックで割ったような新たなフィーチャーを
divided by network traffic.
作るかもしれない。
And so here X5 will take
するとx5は、もしあるマシンが
on a unusually large value
とても大きなCPUロードでありながら
if one of the machines has a
そんなに大きくないネットワークトラフィックの時には
very large CPU load but
異常に大きな値を
not that much network traffic and
とるだろう。
so this will be a
だからこのフィーチャーは
feature that will help your
あなたのアノマリー検出が
anomaly detection capture, a certain type of anomaly.
ある種のアノマリーを検出するのを助ける事になる。
And you can
こんな風にさらに別の
also get creative and come up with other features as well.
フィーチャーも思いつくかもしれない。
Like maybe I have a feature
例えばx6として
x6 thats CPU load
CPUロードを二乗した物を
squared divided by network traffic.
ネットワークトラフィックで割った物を使うかもしれない。
And this would be another variant
これはx5の変種の一つと
of a feature like x5 to try
考えられる。それはマシンの一つが
to capture anomalies where one
とても高いCPUロードにありながら
of your machines has a very
それに見合うネットワークトラフィックが無い
high CPU load, that maybe
物を見分けようと
doesn't have a commensurately large network traffic.
しているフィーチャーだ。
And by creating features like
これらのようなフィーチャーを作る事で
these, you can start to capture
フィーチャーの異常な
anomalies that correspond to
組み合わせを
unusual combinations of values of the features.
捉えていく事が出来る。
So in this video we
このビデオでは
talked about how to and
どうフィーチャーを選び
take a feature, and maybe transform
必要ならアルゴリズムに
it a little bit, so that
食わせる前に
it becomes a bit more Gaussian,
ちょっと変換して
before feeding into an anomaly detection algorithm.
よりガウス分布っぽくするかを議論した。
And also the error analysis
また、新しいフィーチャーを作って
in this process of creating features
異なる種類のアノマリーを捕捉する為の
to try to capture different types of anomalies.
エラー分析の手順も議論した。
And with these sorts of guidelines hopefully that will help you
これらのガイドラインが
to choose good features, to give to
あなたが良いフィーチャーを選び
your anomaly detection algorithm, to
すべてのアノマリーをあなたの検出アルゴリズムが
help it capture all sorts of anomalies.
捕捉出来る一助にならんことを！